Laser diode nonlinear dynamics from…
- semiconductor laser have attracted much attention over the last 40 years
- semiconductor lasers are tools that give an insight into nonlinear dynamics of systems with time delay, and have potential for driving applications based on chaos (reword)
- chaos in lasers could be driven by:
	- external mirror
	- optoelectronic feedback
	- polarisation-rotated optical feedback (PROF)
	- phase conjugate feedback (PCF)
		- reflected light greatly modifies the output

- we use Lang-Kobayashi equations to theoretically investigate the different behaviours
	- these equations are delayed differential equations (DDEs)
	- the parameters drive the different dynamics of the system

PCF
- has attracted attention, and experiments have identified characteristics that are not present in conventional optical feedback (COF):
	- super harmonic self-pulsating solutions
	- high-frequency harmonic pulsing dynamics underlying chaotic low-frequency fluctuations

PCF simulation dynamics dependant on feedback strength:
	- steady state
	- external-cavity-modes (ECMs)
	- chaos
	- low-frequency fluctuations (LFF)
	- extreme events (?)
	- undamped oscillations with frequency close to laser f_RO

ECM in PCF: 
- self-pulsating intensity solutions with period close to integer multiple of the external-cavity round-trip time
- emerge from Hopf bifurcations

- from the ECM limit-cycle solutions, LFFs emerge through secondary bifurcations

FPCF has three different possible dynamics with respect to feedback strength…


<----------------------------------------------
Fast phase response and chaos bandwidth enhancement…
- typical laser, bandwidth is largely limited by relaxation oscillation (RO) frequency
- bandwidth typically persists even when chaos is generated in signal
- driven by the need for high-speed chaos encryption, and many other needs, research is devoted to increasing the bandwidths of semiconductor lasers (SLs)
- injection is most common method to enhance chaos bandwidth

- in SL with optical injection and large feedback strength, intrinsic phase response frequency typically > freq_RO


<----------------------------------------------
Sustained oscillations accompanying polarization switching in laser dynamics
- SLs usually emit linearly polarizaed light -> due to their gain medium and their inherent material anisotropy
- possible for SL structure to be changed. Inducing switching towards an orthogonal polarisation state
	- detrimental in optical communication
	- preferred in:
		- clock recovery
		- secure communication
		- random number generation
- random switching can be triggered by noise and chaos alike

- periodic switching can be achieved through optical pulse pumping, optical injection, and with polarisation rotation of a feedback light

polarisation switching optical feedback (PROF):
- one polarization is filtered while the other one is turned by 90 degrees
- Polarization switching in PROF arises from a Hopf bifurcation creating a square-wave modulation in long-cavity regime



<----------------------------------------------
Relaxation and square-wave oscillations in a semiconductor laser…
- plateau lengths can be controlled by simply changing the delay of the feedback
- transverse electric (TE)
- transverse magnetic (TM)
- …


<----------------------------------------------
High-order external cavity modes and restabilization of a laser diode…
- sequence of bifurcations for laser diode with phase-conjugate feedback wrt. feedback rate
- theory points out that the system restabilizes through a Hopf bifurcation whose frequency is a harmonic of the external cavity frequency
- In PCF the ECMs are oscillating intensity solutions at harmonics offreq_EC, whereas ECMs of laser with COF are steady-state solutions
- large feedback strengths, it has been theoretically shown that the system exhibits ECMs, and that the order of ECMs increases with the feedback strength
- f_ECM = n*f_EC

- report complete experimental bifurcation scenario


<----------------------------------------------
Semiconductor Laser Dynamics for Feedback from a Finite-Penetration-Depth Phase-Conjugate Mirror


<----------------------------------------------
Thesis:
- Introduce concepts of lasers
	- types of interaction:
		- Absorption
		- spontaneous emission
		- stimulated emission
	- require population inversion to ensure electrons are in excited state
		- electrons(materials_{room temp}) < excited
		- through stimulated emission we now able to maintain amplification
		- we achieve population inversion through pumping, either optically from an auxiliary source of light or electricity via a bias current
	- also need a cavity which acts as a resonator
		- resonator is composed of two mirrors, one of which has a transparency
		- the resonator confines photons inside the gain medium, along the direction of propagation to enhance the gain from stimulated emission
			- once the gain > losses, the laser reaches its threshold and starts to emit a coherent beam of light (typical intensity vs pump graph)
				- losses: from absorption in the material, and from photons exiting the cavity















